Finding Aid for Neighborhood Renewal Services of Saginaw records, 1988-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Neighborhood Renewal Services of Saginaw records 1988-2011
Neighborhood Renewal Services of Saginaw.
1 drawer of oversized material
21 linear feet
2010149 Aa 2
Organization established to help revitalize urban neighborhoods of Saginaw, Michigan; records of board; photographs, files relating to Cathedral District Project 2000 and to Community Buildings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group came from the organization (donor no. 10375 ) in June 2010.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Neighborhood Renewal Services (NRS), a non-profit agency dedicated to the revitalization of Saginaw's urban neighborhoods, was founded September 1988. The original mission was to work in a single neighborhood in the central city around Saint Mary's Hospital. From its inception NRS has worked in partnership with Saint Mary's which has provided both guidance and financial support to the revitalization effort.
The initial programs of the organization related to the needs of the citizens within the local neighborhood. Among the early initiatives were youth activity programs, health fairs, and historic home tours. From these beginning NRS began to buy and rehabilitate homes near the hospital. In July 1997, NRS received the first year grant of a three-year commitment to acquire property and demolish abandoned and burned-out buildings, loan money for property improvement projects, give grants to residents to beautify their streets and promote neighborhood improvement projects. This was the Cathedral District Project 2000.
The Cathedral District is part of one of eastside Saginaw's oldest neighborhoods, portions of which have been included in the National Register Historic Districts. The buildings range in age from the 1860s to the early 1960s. Cathedral District Project was intended as a demonstration project to eliminate blight, manage land and improve the appearance and character of the neighborhood. In a letter of 1999, the organization's executive director report that the NRS had purchased 47 properties, demolishing with city assistance blighted buildings and then resold the land to neighbors and businesses. New homes were built on many of the parcels.
In 1999, NRS submitted a proposal to the East Central Province Daughters of Charity for funds to develop a resident leadership program. A one year grant was award to develop a program using the Community Builders leadership training model. As part of this training Community Builders are encouraged to initiate projects that physically impact their neighborhood or "otherwise improve the quality of life for residents in Saginaw's low and moderate income neighborhoods."
The records indicate the organization continued its work through 2011. The office closed in 2012.
The records of Neighborhood Renewal Services have been maintained as received into the following series: Board of Directors Meeting Packets; Cathedral District Project 2000; Community Builders; Downtown Saginaw Farmers Market, Clippings, Visual Materials, Cathedral District Housing Survey, Cathedral District tours, and Topical files. The records which include minutes of meetings, published materials, reports, photographs, and other materials document the efforts of this community group, in partnership with local government and private groups and organizations to deal with the issue of urban decay. One of their principal initiatives documented in the records is the Cathedral District Project 2000. This series of records includes agenda and meeting minutes, photographs, financial information, and published materials. The record group is also of value for its visual documentation of the individual houses and buildings in the Cathedral District of Saginaw. This series includes slides and photographs. There are also photographs in the Cathedral District Housing Survey series which is arranged alphabetically by street name and building number.
Subjects:
Neighborhoods--Michigan--Saginaw.; Saginaw (Mich.); Urban renewal--Michigan--Saginaw.; Neighborhood Renewal Services of Saginaw.
- Board of Directors Meeting Packets
  - July 1988-December 1994, 6 expandable folders (Box 1)
  - 1995-1999, 5 binders (Box 2)
  - 2000-2003, 4 binders (Box 3)
  - 2004-2005, 2 binders (Box 10)
  - 2006-2011, 6 folders (Box 10)
- Cathedral District Project 2000
  - Record books
    - 1997-1999, 10 binders (Box 4)
    - 2000, 2 binders (Box 5)
  - Social Compact Award: information from NRS and Saint Mary's Hospital in support of their application for the award grant circa 1997-1999, 1 folder; 1 binder (Box 5)
    (binder includes articles, reports, correspondence, etc.)
  - Slides and photographs of targeted buildings, 2 binders (Box 5)
- Community Builders
  - Resident Leadership training materials for neighborhood revitalization, 4 binders (Box 6)
  - Code of ordinances, Saginaw, Michigan, 1 binder (Box 6)
  - Record books November 1999-January 2004, 5 binders (Box 7)
    (include reports, photographs, published materials, etc.)
  - Photographs of people and activities and projects, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Grant application materials (Box 8)
- Downtown Saginaw Farmers Market
  - Files relating to the redevelopment of the market at a new location 2002 include design proposals, financial reports, funding applications, background information, clippings (Box 8)
- Clippings
  - 1999-2005 (Box 9)
- Visual Materials
  - Slides of neighborhood houses and other buildings
    (in binders unless otherwise indicated)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 11)
    - 1990 (Box 11)
    - 1990 (rehabilitation projects) (Box 11)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 11)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 12)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 12)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 12)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1 expandable folder (Box 13)
  - Photographs of houses and other projects
    - Cathedral District Update 1998 (Box 13)
    - Farmers' Market (Box 13)
    - Houses 2002 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1 folder; 3 packets (Box 13)
- Cathedral District Housing Survey
  (arranged by name of street)
  - A-H (Box 14)
  - H-M (Box 15)
  - O-T (Box 16)
  - W-miscellaneous (Box 17)
- Cathedral District tours
  - Brochures (Box 17)
  - Working files 1990-1993 (Box 17)
  - Working files 1994-1997 (Box 18)
- Topical files
  - Cathedral Campus Work Group (Box 18)
  - Cathedral District Demonstration Project (Box 18)
  - Cathedral District Impact Tour for Neighborworks America June 14-15, 2005 (Box 18)
  - Community Builders Curriculum and other materials, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Dorothy Richardson Award (Box 19)
  - Downtown Saginaw Farmer's Market (Box 19)
  - East Central Province of Daughters of Charity -- Community Builders (Box 19)
  - East Genesee Avenue Corridor Project (Box 19)
  - Foster G. McGaw Prize 1999 (Box 19)
  - Frank N. Andersen Foundation Grant Application -- Cathedral District Strategic Fund 2003 (Box 19)
  - Home Ownership Promotion Initiative, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Neighborhood reinvestment materials (Box 19)
  - Neighborhood Renewal Services
    - Cathedral District Property Activity (acquisition, demolition, resale) 1997-2006 (Box 19)
    - Historical Overview and Timeline (Box 19)
    - Long-range planning session March 15, 1991 (Box 19)
    - Overview of programs (Box 19)
    - Strategic planning retreat June 6, 2005 (Box 19)
    - 2004 materials (Box 19)
  - Newsletters, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 20)
  - Property acquisition policies and forms (Box 20)
  - Property inventory / mapping reports (Box 20)
  - Publications (Box 20)
  - Reports 1989, undated (Box 20)
  - Report: "Greetings from Saginaw, Michigan: Rebuilding Value and Pride, A Report on Saginaw's Eastside Neighborhoods" February 2007 (Box 20)
  - St. Mary's of Michigan Advisory Board (Box 21)
  - St. Mary's Medical Center annual reports and community service plan (Box 21)
  - St. Mary's Community Service Committee (Box 21)
  - Social Compact Award (Box 21)
    (also include VHS tape)
  - Space Management Committee and Property Improvement Committee (Box 21)
  - Special Projects Requests: South Washington Ave. Corridor Improvement Project FY 2004 (Box 21)
  - Maps of Saginaw, Michigan neighborhoods under study by NRS; include the Cathedral District, the South Washington Target Area, the South Jefferson Avenue Corridor, the St. Mary’s Hospital Study Area, and the New Covenant Target Area; also foam-board display panels, some containing photographs of renewal projects (Map-case 21)